（サクラ）へぇ～　絵なんか描くんだ。
Oh, so you draw.
（サクラ）こんなところで描いてるから
風景画だと思ってたら…。
I thought you were drawing
a landscape since you're outside.
これ　抽象画ね。
But it's an abstract, isn't it?
この絵　タイトルは何ていうの？
So do you have a title for it?
（サイ）さぁ…。
まだ　決めてない？
Well…
You haven't decided on one yet?
（サイ）そんなもの　ないよ…。
I don't know.
正確には　タイトルをつけようとしても
つけられないんだ。
To be exact,
I couldn't title one of my drawings
even if I wanted to.
何も　思い浮かばない…
何も感じないんだよ。
Nothing comes to mind.
I don't feel anything.
（ナルト）フンッ！　そんな絵…
たいしたことねえってばよ。
Your drawing's...
nothing special!
そうですね。
君の　おチンチンと同じですよ。
You're right.
Just like your "equipment."
くっ…　正直に　はっきり言う。
I'm going to be honest with you!
俺は　てめえが嫌いだ！
I don't like you.
文句があんなら　作り笑いなんか
しねえで→
If you've got a problem,
just drop the fake smile
正直に　はっきり言いやがれ！
and tell me straight to my face!
喧嘩なら　いつでも買ってやる！
I'll fight you anytime, anywhere!
そんなものないよ。
I don't have a problem with you.
君のことなんて
ほんとに　なんとも思ってない。
I don't care about you at all.
《中心部は　順調に作業が
進んでいるようだな…》
Work on the central part of the city
seems to be going smoothly.
Sai's Day Off
《サイ：里の周辺部は　まだまだ
人手が足りていないか…》
There's not enough help
along the perimeter of the village.
≪ようし！　お宝探し始め～！
All right!
Let's start the treasure hunt!
≪お～っ！
– Yeah!
Hello? Is there a lost doll in here?
もしも～し？　迷子になった
お人形さんとかいませんか？
I'll take you back home with me.
私が　連れて帰ってあげますよ。
（サイ）こんなところで遊んでちゃ
危ないよ。
It's dangerous to play here.
えっ！？
がれきが崩れてきたら　大変だ。
The rubble might fall and
cause it to cave-in!
《別に　おどかすつもりは
なかったのにな…》
I didn't mean to scare her.
どうしたんだ？
What happened?
That man said...
あのお兄ちゃんが…。
Wow! You're good!
うわぁ～　上手！
《子供…　さっきの？》
It's the children from earlier!
Are you a manga artist?
お兄さん　漫画家？
お絵描き屋さん？
Or are you a painter?
もしかして　さすらいの旅人？
Or are you a wandering traveler?
（サイ）いや…　違うよ。
No, I'm not.
Then what are you
doing drawing here?
じゃあ　なんでこんなところで
絵を描いてたの？
僕は今日　お休みをもらったから→
I had the day off today,
里の様子を見に　ここまで
足を延ばして来てみたんだけど。
so I took a walk to see
how things were going in the village.
ねぇねぇ　他の絵も見せて。
Hey, hey can you show us
your other drawings?
別に　人に見せるために
描いたものじゃないから…。
Well, my drawings are
not for others to see.
《まずい！　このパターンは…》
Oh no, I shouldn't have
said it like that.
わぁ～っ。
フゥ　なんとかごまかせた。
I managed to fool them.
待て。　あ～っ。
捕まえた。
Wait!
I got you!
そのまま　そのまま。　動くなよ。
Stay, stay. Don't move!
あっ！　オケツ破れちゃった。
My pants just ripped!
あんた
昨日も洋服破いて帰ったでしょ。
Hey! You went home yesterday
with torn clothes too.
ヘッ　お父ちゃんは子供はそれくらい
元気があったほうがいいってさ。
My dad says kids should be energetic and
active enough to have stuff like that happen.
毎日毎日
洋服を縫わなきゃならない→
Put yourself in
your mom's place sometimes.
She's the one who has to
mend them day in and day out!
お母さんの苦労も考えなさいよ。
あ～あ　始まった。
うっせんだよ　ブス！
Uh-uh, here we go again.
Shut up, ugly!
誰がブスですって。
Who are you calling "ugly"?!
間違い　間違い。
待て　こら！
– My mistake, my mistake!
– Hey wait!
フフッ。
しゃんなろ～！
イッテ～。
Cha!
Ouch!
《サイ：なんか
ナルトとサクラを見ているようだな》
It's just like watching
Naruto and Sakura.
このアンポンタン。
イテ～ッ　頭破けた。
I'll teach you!
Ouch!
My head got hit!
《そういえば　僕もサクラに
殴られたことがあったな》
That's right. Sakura hit me
hard like that too.
ごめんなさい。
ナルトのことは許してあげて。
I'm sorry.
Please forgive Naruto.
別に　なんとも思ってないよ。
It's okay. It doesn't bother me.
そう　よかった。
Really? Thank goodness.
私のことは許さなくていいから。
I don't care if
you forgive me or not.
騙されたな。
君のさっきの作り笑い。
You fooled me, with that
fake smile of yours earlier.
《あれは　冗談ですまされない
レベルだったけど》
Although that was much
too intense just for a joke.
これってお兄ちゃんのお友達？
Are these your friends?
え？　いや
お友達というより仲間かな。
Huh? Well no,
I guess they're my comrades.
仲間ってお友達じゃないの？
Aren't comrades your friends?
う～ん。
《サイ：難しい問題だな》
That's a difficult question.
The bond that Naruto feels
with Sasuke…
《サイ：ナルトが感じている
サスケ君とのつながり。
その強さの訳を　僕は本当に
実感していないのかもしれない》
Perhaps I've never experienced
anything that strong.
サイ　お前はすっこんでろ。
Sai, stay out of this.
ナルト　君がサスケなんかのために
殴られてやる必要はない。
Naruto, you don't have to
get punched for Sasuke's sake.
サスケは
君を傷つけるばかりじゃないか。
Sasuke keeps hurting you
over and over again.
If I were you…
僕なら…。
I just felt I should do something,
as a member of Team Kakashi.
《でも　カカシ班の仲間として
何かしなければと思った。
けれど　そのせいでナルトとサクラを→
But because of that,
I think I made things more painful
for Naruto and Sakura.
かえって苦しめる結果に
なったのかもしれない》
ウッ…。
It's like Naruto has
been shouldering
ナルトは君との約束を
ずっと背負ってるようだった。
the burden of his promise to you.
一生背負う気で
いるみたいだった。
As though he intends to bear
that burden for the rest of his life.
君がナルトに何を
言ったのかは知らない。
I don't know what you told Naruto.
でもそれは　まるで僕のされている
ものと同じ呪印のように感じた。
But it's no different from
what was done to me.
It's like a Curse Mark.
Sasuke is the source of Naruto's agony.
ナルトを苦しめてるのはサスケだけど
君もなんじゃないのかい？
But aren't you a part of it too?
サスケ君はどんどん離れていくだけ。
Sasuke keeps getting farther
and farther away from me.
でも　ナルト。　あんたはいつも
私のそばにいてくれた。
But Naruto,
you've always stuck by my side
and cheered me up.
私を励ましてくれた。
私　気づいたの。
I finally realized, Naruto,
ナルト　あんたの本当の姿に。
your true self.
でも　サスケ君は罪を重ね
私の心を砕くだけ。
Meanwhile, Sasuke keeps
adding to his list of crimes,
and breaking my heart.
どんどん別の遠い人になっていく。
Continually becoming more
of a stranger.
でもナルト　あんたのことは
こうして触れていられる。
But Naruto, I'm able to
be close to you like this.
You comfort me.
安らぎをくれる。
I care about you,
from the bottom of my heart.
今は　あんたのことが
心の底から…。
Cut it out, Sakura.
This joke isn't funny at all!
いいかげんにしろ　サクラちゃん。
そんな冗談は笑えねえって
言ってんだよ。
俺は　自分に
嘘をつくようなやつは嫌いだ。
I hate people who lie
to themselves!
《僕のせいで　サクラはひとりで→
As a result, Sakura set out alone
to settle things with Sasuke.
サスケと決着をつけようと
行動を起こし→
After I told Naruto about
Sakura's true intentions,
ナルトには
サクラの本心を伝えたせいで→
he was in such turmoil,
that he lost consciousness.
意識を失って倒れるほどの
ショックを与えてしまった。
これが本当の友達だったなら
違うやり方があったのか…》
If I had been a true friend,
would I have handled it differently?
ここらへんは来たことがないな。
I've never been here before.
We need to gather
more workers tomorrow.
明日は
もっと人手を集めねえとな。
Wouldn't it be faster if we used
Paper Bombs to clear everything?
起爆札で
吹っ飛ばしちまったほうが→
早いんじゃねえか？
バ～カ　そんなことしたら→
Idiot! If you do that,
you'll blast away everything!
全部　吹っ飛ばしちまうだろうが。
駄目だ。
– We can't do that!
– Yeah, you're right.
あぁ　そうか。
おう　すまねえな兄ちゃん。
Oh, excuse us, fella.
《こんなところにまで被害が…》
So the damage extends this far.
《ひどいな》
How terrible.
あの…。
By chance, are you related to
the family who lived here?
もしや　この家のお身内の方で？
いえ。
たまたま通りがかっただけで。
No, I'm just passing through.
あぁ　すみません。
Oh, pardon me.
Well, I live next door.
いえ　私は
隣のもんでございますが→
I was going to let you know
if you were family,
お身内の方なら　ご家族は
安全な場所におられると→
that they are staying at
the evacuation shelter.
お伝えしようと　はぁ　思いまして。
よかったですね　ご無事で。
I'm glad they're okay.
Yes, although their house
is totally ruined.
えぇ。　でも　お屋敷は
このありさまで→
明日にも　解体作業が
行われると聞きました。
I understand it's going to
be demolished tomorrow.
I see.
そうですか。
They say all things eventually decay.
もの皆すべて
いずれ朽ちるとはいえ→
おさみしいものです。
But this is still so tragic.
Everyone is gone,
《家主を失った家…
寂しく感じる》
and I can feel the loneliness.
こんばんは。
Good evening.
何やってんのよ？
What are you doing?
It's obvious just by looking
that no one lives here.
誰も住んでないことは
一目瞭然じゃない。
いや　なにね…。
No, but I was thinking more
along the lines of
something else "living" here.
別の何かが住み着いてるんじゃ
ないのかな～って。
それって幽霊の類のこと？
いるわけないよ。
Do you mean ghosts?
That's ridiculous.
Keep your opinions to yourself!
てめえは　口挟むんじゃねえ！
Okay, okay.
We'll be spending the night here.
（ヤマト）はいはい。
今夜は　ここで１泊ね。
You are such an idiot!
（サクラ）ほんと　バカなんだから。
サイ。
Sai.
ちょっと　話があるってばよ。
I need to talk to you.
今から俺と本気で戦え。
Sai, I want you to fight me seriously.
そんなことして
何の意味があるんです？
And what good would that do?
Just fight me and
you'll understand.
やってみりゃ　わかるってばよ。
そこまでしなくても　君の実力は
もうわかってますから。
I'm aware of your strength
without having to do that.
Then try and dodge me!
なら　かわしてみろ！
影分身の術！
Shadow Clone Jutsu!
まったく…。
Damn it.
I see.
《なるほど
超獣戯画を使わせないつもりか》
He's trying to prevent me from
using my Super Beast Scroll.
《悪いが　これで退散させて…。
Sorry, but I'm leaving right now.
しつこい…》
He's persistent.
《決着をつけるしかないか》
I have no choice
but to settle this.
てや～っ！
（ヤマト）ナルト！　サイ！
Naruto, Sai!
（ヤマト）姿が見えないと思ったら
こんなことか。
One minute you're both gone,
and this is what I find
you two doing?
Really, how many times do you
have to make me repeat myself?
まったく…　何度も同じことを
言わせるんじゃないよ。
仕掛けたのは　ナルトのほうだろ？
You started it, didn't you, Naruto?
サイも軽々しく
挑発に乗るんじゃないよ。
And Sai, don't accept
a challenge so quickly.
まっ　しかし→
Anyway, I'd say this match…
この勝負　ナルトの勝ちだな。
goes to Naruto!
うぉ～っ！
ハァ　ハァ　ハァ…。
見直したよ
ヤマト隊長に化けるとは…。
I misjudged you.
I never thought that you'd transform
into Captain Yamato.
君が　こんなだまし討ちみたいな
手を使うなんてねぇ。
I didn't expect you to be so sly.
すっかり騙されたよ。
You totally fooled me.
もっと直接的で
バカ正直な戦い方しか→
All this time,
I thought you were only capable
of straightforward
and direct combat.
君は
できないとばかり思っていたから。
だからといって
こんな勝ち負けだけで→
But don't think for a minute,
that this kind of victory means
you're stronger than I am.
僕より強いんだって
言いたいのなら→
それは　ただの自己満足だよ。
If you do, you're just being smug.
そんなんじゃねえってばよ。
It's not like that at all.
ヤマト隊長が言ったろ
俺とお前は　チームだって。
Remember what Captain Yamato said.
You and me, we're a team.
１人が動くときは
相棒が　それを援護する→
When one moves,
the partner backs him up.
We have a buddy system.
バディシステムで行動するって。
この先　もし
サスケを連れ戻そうとするのを→
From now on,
as we try to get Sasuke back,
if an enemy appears
and gets in our way,
邪魔する敵が現れたとき→
we need to know how
we fight to be more effective.
お互いの戦い方知ってたほうが
より動きやすいだろ。
俺より　いつも冷静なお前なら→
You're more level-headed than I am.
You might figure out a way to
make better use of my strengths.
俺の力を利用した　うまい戦い方を
思いつくかもしれねえしな。
そういうことも
あるんじゃねえかと思ってよ。
That was in the back of my mind.
それで　サスケ君が戻ってくれば→
And then, if Sasuke returns,
I'll be able to leave
Team Kakashi, right?
僕も早く
カカシ班から抜けられますしね。
あぁ！　せいせいすらぁ！
Yeah, I can't wait.
《ナルトは必ず
サスケ君を連れ戻せると信じていた。
Naruto firmly believed that
he would bring Sasuke back.
その思いの強さは
一緒に行動するようになって→
And after working together,
I started to feel the depth
of his conviction.
徐々に感じることができた。
でも　サスケ君のほうは…》
But as for Sasuke…
((はじめまして。
僕は　サイと言います。
How do you do?
My name is Sai.
(君が　うちはサスケ君…。
（サスケ）失せろ！))
So you're Sasuke Uchiha?
Get lost.
サスケ君！
Sasuke!
《冷たく　恐ろしい目…。
Such cold, frightening eyes.
でも　その奥で　冷たさは　まるで
炎のように揺らめいていた》
And deep within, that coldness
was like a smoldering fire.
Naruto must have seen
those eyes too.
《ナルトも　あの目を見たはず》
((俺を追い回す暇があったら
修業でもしてりゃあよかったのに。
All the time you wasted
pursuing me
might have been
better spent training,
なぁ？　ナルト。
right, Naruto?
だから今度は　俺の気まぐれで→
That's why this time around,
my whim is telling me that
you'll lose your life.
(お前は命を落とすんだぜ))
《あの目を見た時→
When I saw those eyes,
I knew that no words
could reach Sasuke.
サスケ君には　何の呼びかけも
届かないと思った。
けれど　ナルトは…　ナルトの気持は
今も　少しも変わっていない》
But Naruto's feelings
didn't change at all.
((昔　俺は
サスケのことが大嫌いだった。
I used to really hate Sasuke.
でも　一緒にいて　ほんとは
すごく楽しかったんだってばよ。
But it was actually fun being with him.
あいつは　誰よりも
俺のことを認めてくれた一人だ。
He's the only person who
acknowledged me,
more than anyone else.
サスケは　俺の友達だから。
Sasuke is my friend.
やっとできた
大切なつながりだから。
It's a special bond
I was finally able to make.
だからって　大蛇丸相手に…。
腕がもがれりゃ　蹴り倒す。
足がもがれりゃ　噛み倒す。
首がもがれりゃ　にらみ倒す。
目がもがれりゃ　呪い倒す。
たとえ　バラバラにされようが→
(俺は大蛇丸から　サスケを
奪い返してやるんだってばよ))
《サイ：それまで　嘘や裏切りの
世界で生きてきた僕に→
ナルトは　人を信頼することの
大切さを思い出させてくれた。
そのつながりの強さを
確かめたくて→
僕は任務に反して
サスケ君を連れ戻す決断をした》
《そして　今も
カカシ班の一員として　ここにいる》
((カカシ：火影の連絡には→
ナルトの行動は
一切伏せておいてくれ。
（カカシ）何も動きはないと。
僕は　まだ　あなたには
信用されていないみたいですね。
ダンゾウの部下で
ナルトの見張り役の君だ。
だが　お前は　俺たち
カカシ第七班の一員でもある。
(信じてるよ))
《何だろう？　この感じ》
《ナルト　サスケ　サクラ…。
この先　どうなるのか
わからないけど→
３人は　誰にも断ち切れないほどの
強い絆で結ばれている気がする。
そして　僕も　いつか…》
((まったく…　君は　よく似ている。
え？
兄さんにだよ。
口やかましく
慌てんぼうで　品がなくて→
それに　おチ…
まぁ　それは　いいや。
だけど　そう
何をするにも必死だった。
君を見ていると
なんだか　兄さんのことを…。
♪～
それって…。
思い出した…　思い出したんだ…。
兄さんに見せたかった。
(２人の…　夢の絵を…))
♪～
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
美空ひばりです。
では　最後まで
ごゆっくり　お楽しみください。